<?xml version="1.0"?>

<test xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
      xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
      xmlns:s="http://cm.bell-labs.com/stat/S4"
      xmlns:c="http://www.c.org"
>

<title>Dynamically Creating XSL Functions</title>
The <s:package>Sxslt</s:package> package makes only a few XSL
functions available to access R. These are sufficient to access all of
R's functionality and in that respect they are the primitives for
interfacing XSL to R.
However, the resulting <quote>code</quote> in the XSL 
stylesheets can be a little awkward.
For example, 
<verb>
 r:date()
</verb>
might be preferred by authors and  readers
alike to the functionally equivalent
<verb>
 r:call('date')
</verb>
For one, the first is shorter and more obvious.
Secondly, it avoids additional quoting of
the function name.

<p/>

We could of course register a large number of R functions so that they
would be available directly to the XSL author. However, what can we do
about functions that aren't registered, functions from newly added
packages, and a user's own functions?  The simple answer is that we
provide an XSL function by which XSL (and XML) authors can register R
functions with the XSLT engine.  Specifically, one can create an
<quote>alias</quote> in XSL for the S function by giving its name.
The XSL function used to register a new function is
<xsl:function>r:register</xsl:function>.
One calls this with the name of the R function to be registered
and this name is also used as the name of the XSL function.

<p/>

A simple example may help. Suppose we want to make the S function
<s:functionRef>date</s:functionRef> available as a
<quote>directly</quote> callable XSL function.  Then we can call
<xsl:function>register</xsl:function> and give it the name of the S
function to be registered. In this case, the
<xsl:function>register</xsl:function> creates an XSL function with the
name <xsl:function>date</xsl:function> and whne this is called, it
will invoke the S function of the same name.
The XSL code to register the function is
<verb>
  r:register("date")
</verb>
and is usually invoked from the 
<xsl:attribute>test</xsl:attribute> attribute
of an <xsl:element>if</xsl:element>
element.

(We will perform the registration in this document
with a rule in <file>register.xsl</file>
<r:register name="date" function="date"/>
)

<p/>

In the <xsl:function>date</xsl:function> example, we have a one-to-one
correspondence between the name of the XSL function and the S
function.  This is often convenient, but sometimes we will want the
two to be separate.  If we want to associate or alias an S function
with a different name in XSL we can provide a second argument to
<xsl:function>register</xsl:function>.  The first argument gives the
name of the new XSL function to create.  The second
argument is the name of the S function to use to implement that
XSL function.
For example, supppose we want to call the S function
<s:function>date</s:function> from XSL but
would like to have a call of the form
<verb>
 r:Date()
</verb>
(i.e. the first letter capitalized).
Then, we call <xsl:function>register</xsl:function>
with <literal>"Date"</literal> as the first argument
and <literal>"date"</literal> as the second argument,
i.e.
<verb>
 r:register("Date", "date")
</verb>

Again, we register this from this document.
<r:register name="Date" function="date"/>

<p/>

A final wrinkle on registration allows us to associate S functions
that we define in the XML and XSL documents rather than pre-existing
functions in S.  The second argument to
<xsl:function>register</xsl:function> can be a string containing an S
expression that defines (and whose value is) an S function.  The
underlying <xsl:function>register</xsl:function> function checks to
see if this second argument is the name of existing function anywhere
in the R search path. If so, it uses that.  Otherwise,
<s:functionRef>registerXSLFunction</s:functionRef> attempts to parse
and evaluate the <s:arg>function</s:arg> argument and if it returns an
S function, it register that.

As a simple-minded example, let's define an XSL function
<xsl:function>search</xsl:function> that returns the output from the
corresponding S function, but concatenates the different names of the
elements on the search path into a single, comma-separate string.

<verb>
 r:register("search", "function() paste(search(), collapse=', ')) 
</verb>
This allows us to easily modify and use S functions that do not provide a suitable
return type from within our XML and XSL documents.

<r:register name="search" 
            function="function() paste(search(), collapse=', ') "/>


<p/>
Now that we have created these 3 functions,
let's call them.

We can invoke the XSL function <xsl:function>date</xsl:function>
which returns <foo/>

<p/>
We can call the XSL function <xsl:function>Date</xsl:function>
which will call the R function <s:function>date</s:function>.
<date/>

<p/>
We next invoke the XSL function <xsl:function>search</xsl:function>.
<search/>


<title>Registering Functions Externally</title>

We have registered XSL functions from within the target
document. Obviously, we can do this from the XSL file and reap the
benefits of having this apply to all target XML files.  In the same
spirit, we can put the function registration code in S code.  Then we
can register numerous functions by sourcing a file or calling a
top-level registration function from XSL, or simply having the
registration happen when R starts via the <file>.Rprofile</file> or a
<s:functionRef>.First.lib</s:functionRef> function of a library that
is attached.
The file <file>register.R</file> illustrates how this works.

<externalRegister />

<title>The Registration and Invocation Mechanism</title> 

The reason that we can interchangeably register XSL functions from
XML, XSL and R is because of the mechanism used for registration.  The
infrastructure is quite simple.  We define an R function --
<s:functionRef>registerXSLFunction</s:functionRef> -- which is the
primary entry point.  This handles the different cases of when a
second argument is provided and whether it is a name, a function or an
S expression that evaluates to the function to be registered.  Then,
this function calls a C routine
(<c:routine>RSXSLT_registerFunction</c:routine>) which stores the name
and function in an internal table, and registers the name (and a
generic handler) with the XSLT engine. 

<p/> The <s:functionRef>registerXSLFunction</s:functionRef> function
makes it easy for S programmers to register XSL functions.  This is
how we can add functions from S scripts and libraries.  Since
<s:functionRef>registerXSLFunction</s:functionRef> is an S function,
we can also call it from XSL. And the XSL function
<xsl:function>register</xsl:function> is exactly this, a simple call
to <s:functionRef>registerXSLFunction</s:functionRef> using the basic
mechanism for calling any R function from XSL.  So this establishes
the XSL interface to the registration functionality.

<p/>

When one of these registered XSL functions is invoked by the XSLT
engine, the generic handler routine we associated with the function
when registering it with the XSLT engine is called.  This routine
retrieves the S function associated with the XSL function name being
called.  Then it calls that S function with the arguments from XSL
and returns the value as a suitable XSL object, when possible.

</test>
